g.11
Ukrainian Historical and Educational Center of NJ Archives
Vasyl' Chaplenko papers
Bulk, 1970-1990
1936-1990
g.11
Ukrainian Historical and Educational Center of NJ Archives
4.1 Linear feet 8 boxes
This collection houses the personal and professional papers of the writer, linguist, and editor Vasyl' Chaplenko. It documents his studies of the Ukrainian language, politics, and literature through typescripts of his articles, his correspondence, and through his large collection of annotated newspaper and periodical articles.
Chaplenko, Vasyl', 1900-1990
Related Archival Materials
Some of Chaplenko's writings can also be found in the collections of the Ukrainian Academy of Sciences (UVAN) in New York, the Shevchenko Scientific Society (NTSh-A) in New York, the New York Public Library, and Winnipeg University.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for researcher use. Please contact the archivist (archives@ukrhec.org) for more information and to make arrangements.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Anna Krawczuk, stepdaughter of Vasyl' Chaplenko.
Scope and Contents
This collection houses the papers of the Ukrainian American writer, linguist, and editor Vasyl' Chaplenko, primarily from the last decades of his life. It contains typescript copies of his many articles on politics, literature, linguistics, and Ukrainian scholarship, as well as works of fiction. It also includes personal and family correspondence, photographs, and an extensive collection of periodicals and newspaper clippings, many of which have his handwritten annotations.
Biographical/Historical note
Vasyl' Chaplenko (Василь Чапленко), also known as Vasyl' Chaplia (Василь Чапля) was a Ukrainian and Ukrainian American scholar, linguist, writer, and editor. He was born on March 18, 1900 in Mylolaivka, Ekaterynoslav governate, Russian Empire (today Dnipropetrovs'k oblast', Ukraine). He attended the Teacher's Seminary in Pavlohrad, and the Pedagogical Institute in Dnipropetrovs'k. He became head of the Department of Linguistics at the Pedagogical Institute of Luhans'k, and in 1933 moved to the Pedagogical Institute of Ashkhabad (Turkmenistan). From 1937 to 1941 he was Dean and professor in the Department of Linguistics at the Pedagogical Institutes of Voroshilovsk and Piatigorsk.
As a Displaced Person, he taught General Linguistics and Ukrainian at the Institute of Modern Languages in Augsburg, Germany and edited the newspaper "Nashe Zhyttia". After emigrating to the United States in the 1950s, he served as Chairman and Professor at the Ukrainian Technical Institute in New York, and editor of the Sunday Supplement of the newspaper "Svoboda".
Arrangement
Arranged in eight series, as follows:
Articles, essays, and lectures
Writings on linguistics
Fiction, verse, and theatrical works
Notebooks
Correspondence
Photographs
Third-party materials
Published materials, clippings, and ephemera
- Articles, essays, and lectures, Bulk, 1970-1990; circa 1960-1990; Series 1.; 1.25 Linear feet 31 folders (Box 1, Folder 1-11, Box 3, Folder 1-9, Box 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Typescripts, primarily of articles on topics of politics, literature, linguistics, and Ukrainian scholarship, many with handwritten annotations, corrections, and additions. Also includes a few short fiction works and poetry, as well as occasional correspondence with publishers, editorial offices, and colleagues, and reprints and newspaper clippings (often with handwritten annotations).
- Writings on linguistics, circa 1970-late 1980s; Series 2.; 0.25 Linear feet 6 folders (Box 3, Folder 10, Box 4, Folder 1-5)
  Typescripts (many with handwritten annotations) and handwritten notes on etymologies of ethnonyms, names of places and regions, and surnames; his "Adyghe theory"; draft for a Ukrainian etymological dictionary; and other related topics. Also includes a small number of letters.
- Fiction, verse, and theatrical works, Series 3.; 0.25 Linear feet 5 folders
  Typescripts of unpublished works, typescripts of published works, and copies of published works with revisions.
  - "Gava Ïs'ko" (1984 revision) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "Bezorudavka" (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "Pyvoriz" (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Theatrical works, 2 folders (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
- Notebooks, Series 4. (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, Series 5.; 0.3 Linear feet 12 folders
  - General correspondence, Bulk, 1977-1986; 1951-1990; 0.25 Linear feet 8 folders (Box 5, Folder 4-11)
    Incoming and outgoing letters to friends and colleagues in the US and abroad (Great Britain and Australia). Also includes typescripts of some articles and writings.
  - Family correspondence and documents, 1935-1989; 4 folders
    - Natalia Rudnyts'ka Chaplenko correspondence, 1947-1950 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      Letters from Vasyl' Chaplenko to Natalia Rudnyts'ka Chaplenko and Rev. Dr. Aldo Rudnyts'kyi. Letters from Ivan Korol' to Vasyl' Chaplenko regarding Natalia Rudnyts'ka Chaplenko.
    - Natalia Rudnyts'ka Chaplenko documents, 1935-1951 (Box 5, Folder 13)
      Identification cards, Green Card, naturalization Declaration of Intention, calendars, address books, and ephemera.
    - Natalia Rudnyts'ka Chaplenko funeral records, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Includes condolence book, photographs, funeral home records, and letters.
    - Natalia Osinska Chaplenko correspondence, 1986-1989 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Photographs, 1936-1970; Series 6. (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Third-party materials, Series 7. (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Published materials, clippings, and ephemera, 1975; Series 8.; 1.5 Linear feet 22 folders, approximately 40 bound volumes, and 1 object
  This series primarily contains published materials, either in the form of complete journal issues, clippings, or photocopies. These include articles by Chaplenko and others, and many of them have handwritten annotations by Chaplenko.
  - Pre-1950 publications, 1935-1947; 2 folders (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
  - Complete issues of journals, 1.1 Linear feet (Box 7, Box 8)
  - Reprints, clippings, and photocopies of journal articles, 4 folders (Box 6, Folder 7-10)
  - Yukhym Mykhailiv exhibit catalog, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper clippings, 0.3 Linear feet 12 folders (Box 7, Folder 1-11, Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Ephemera, 2 folders (Box 6, Folder 13-14)
  - Wall hanging depicting a crane (Box 8)
  - Original box/folder lists (Box 6, Folder 15)